Guide to the Americans For Immigrant Justice Records, 1982-2020; 1982-ongoing and undated RL.00035
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Americans For Immigrant Justice records
1982-2020; 1982-ongoing
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center
Americans for Immigrant Justice
Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
RL.00035
103 Linear Feet
Americans for Immigrant Justice (formerly Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center [FIAC]) is a not-for-profit legal assistance organization dedicated to protecting and promoting the basic human rights of immigrants of all nationalities. The Americans for Immigrant Justice records span the years of 1980-2017. The collection contains project files and correspondence regarding immigrant detention policy and conditions in the state of Florida, particularly concerning the Haitian community; legal documents regarding the same, including restricted and confidential legal files; and audiovisual material produced by or for AIJ. The bulk of materials are organized by subject and detention facility.
23625 Items
Access Restrictions
The Restricted Files Series is restricted. Researchers must receive prior authorization from donor in order to access the material in this series. Please contact Rubenstein Research Services to request access. All other series are unrestricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Americans For Immigrant Justice Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2011 and 2018.
Historical Note
Americans for Immigrant Justice (formerly Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center (FIAC)) is a not-for-profit legal assistance organization dedicated to protecting and promoting the basic human rights of immigrants of all nationalities.
Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center (FIAC) was founded in 1996 because of pending restrictions and funding cuts to Legal Services Corporation (LSC) funded agencies, which prevented many organizations in the state of Florida from serving the immigrant population. Sweeping changes in immigration law and welfare reform also increased the demand for services from FIAC. In 2011 After 15 years of helping immigrants obtain legal status, successfully litigating their unjust treatment and pressing for constructive immigration laws and policy, the Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center (FIAC) became Americans for Immigrant Justice (AI Justice for short and Americanos Por Justicia Inmigrante in Spanish) to better reflect the national focus and depth of their work.
Collection Overview
The Americans for Immigrant Justice (AIJ) records, formerly the Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center (FIAC), span the years of 1980-2017. This collection contains extensive documentation of the events and crises surrounding asylum, deportation, detention and abuses that took place within Florida detention centers from the years 1980 to 2017, as well as documentation regarding issues of repatriation. It records the efforts of AIJ to advocate on behalf of immigrant and refugee populations, mainly in Florida, during this time. The majority of material in this collection deals with Haitians seeking asylum in the U.S., but also includes major material on Cuban and Central American refugees, then minor files on Chinese, Middle Eastern, and other immigrant populations. Many files focus on Cheryl Little's work with child refugees and detainees and their asylum claims, and on discrimination against female immigrants. Files also include material on interdiction at sea and related court documents, government immigration policy pre- and post-9/11, documentation on hunger strikes at various facilities, material related to the Haitian Boat crises, and documentation of raids on immigrant populations. The detention facilities of particular concern in this collection include Guantanamo, Krome, and Turner Guilford Knight correctional facilities, as well as Florida's county jails.
The collection contains legal documents related to the activity of AIJ, including affidavits of detainees held in Florida facilities, and other court documents, such as court pleadings and briefings; reports on facility conditions; correspondence, including correspondence between detainees and their families, letters from concerned citizens, and formal correspondence between AIJ and other organizations and officials; case studies and reports on immigration and refugee crises, and reports of abuses and conditions in Florida detention facilities; FBI interviews with detainees; related articles and speeches; restricted material, including medical records; and promotional and educational videos produced by or for AIJ, documentary footage of missions and events, and press conference and news footage.
The series in this collection include the Detention Series, the Immigrant and Refugees Series, the Restricted Series, the General Organizational Records Series, the Audiovisual Series and the Photographic Materials Series. The bulk of the material for this collection belongs to the Detention Series and the Immigrant and Refugees Series.
Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Alien detention centers -- United States; Immigration advocates -- Florida; Videocassettes; Legal documents -- Refugees -- United States; Color photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Women immigrants -- Discrimination -- United States; Refugees -- Haiti; Women immigrants -- Abuse of; Repatriation -- Haiti; Unaccompanied refugee children -- United States; Return migration -- Haiti; Refugees -- Cuba; Detention of persons -- Government policy -- United States; Asylum, Right of; Immigrants -- United States; Hunger strikes -- Detention of persons -- United States; Prisons -- Florida; Maritime law -- United States; Refugees -- Civil rights; Immigrants -- Florida -- Miami; Immigration enforcement -- United States; Immigration Lawyers; Central Americans -- Legal status, laws, etc -- United States; Boat people -- Government policy -- United States; Unaccompanied immigrant children -- Legal status, laws, etc -- United States; Refugees -- Colombia; Refugees -- China; Deportation -- United States; Prisoners -- Medical care -- United States; Immigration enforcement -- Mexican-American Border Region; Emigration and immigration law -- United States; Undocumented immigrant children -- Legal status, laws, etc -- United States; Refugees -- Middle East; Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp; Krome Detention Center; Little, Cheryl; Danticat, Edwidge, 1969- -- Family; Meek, Carrie P., 1926-; González, Elián, 1993-; Reno, Janet, 1938-2016; Graham, Bob, 1936-; Ros-Lehtinen, Ileana; Ashcroft, John D., 1942-; Smith, William French, 1917-1990; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Broward Transitional Center; Turner Guilford Knight Correctional Center.
- Detention Series, 1982-2002
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains documents related to detention facilities holding immigrant and refugee populations of interest to Florida Immigration Advocacy Center, particularly Haitian populations. The series focuses on Krome, Turner Guilford Knight, and Guantanamo detention facilities as well as county jails and other facilities holding immigrants and refugees. Many files deal with allegations of abuse and mismanagement within the facilities. Files include legal documents such as affidavits and court records and other materials such as newspaper articles, correspondence, government reports, and PR materials. Also included are files related to Haitian asylum and repatriation and materials related to Guantanamo children and child refugees. Sensitive and confidential material has been moved to the Restricted Files series. Files are arranged in approximate alphabetical order.
  - Guantanamo Subseries, 1992-1997
    Subseries contains materials related to Guantanamo detention facility, particularly with regard to the Haitian population and child refugees detained at Guantanamo. The subseries includes affidavits, attorney statements, emergency action and funding requests, reports on facility conditions, correspondence, press releases and published reports.
    - Action/Support for Guantanamo minors (Box 1)
    - Ad Hoc Committee (Box 1)
    - Guantanamo Affidavits (clean copy) trip: 1994 Dec. 6-10 (Box 1)
    - Guantanamo Affidavits (clean copy) trip: 1995 Jan. 18-20 (Box 1)
    - Articles, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Assisting refugees at Guantanamo, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Guantanamo Children Informational Packet, 1995 April 25 (Box 1)
    - Donna Abbott - Guantanamo reports (Box 1)
    - Double backers and returnees new article (Box 1)
    - Emergency funding to assist Guantanamo detainees settling in Florida (Box 1)
    - Guantanamo, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Guantanamo Children - emergency action requests (Box 1)
      Amnesty and Tap Tap meeting.
    - Guantanamo Children - flights to Guantanamo (Box 1)
      Air Sunshine.
    - Guantanamo Children - rally protesting detention, 1995 Jan. 7 (Box 1)
    - Guantanamo Children - team background information (Box 1)
      When in Haiti.
    - Fate returnees (Box 1)
    - Guantanamo - forms (Box 1)
    - General - Gray, William (Box 1)
    - General - Guantanamo reports (Box 1)
      Background, etc.
    - General information (Box 1)
    - Guantanamo's H's-M's - Reparole and EAD, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Haitian asylum: Coven (Box 2)
      Beyer memo.
    - Haitian asylum/country conditions, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Haitians denied citizenship (Box 2)
    - Haitian Guantanamo cases/A.O., 1997 (Box 2)
    - Haiti report, 1995 (Box 2)
      Karla Pearcy, 1995 Aug. 8.
    - Haiti trip - repatriated Haitians (Box 2)
    - Haitian detainees, December 1995 (Box 81)
    - Interview/returnees, 1992 Feb. (Box 2)
      Originals, etc.
    - Letters: Congressional etc., 1994 Nov. - 1995 July (Box 2)
    - Letters - Reno, 1995 (Box 2)
      U.S. Attorney General.
    - Letters - Waxman packet, 1995 July (Box 2)
    - Meissner's open letter to Haitian community, 1994 August 5 (Box 2)
    - Memos, reports, and letters on regulations and policy in Guantanamo (Box 2)
    - Mildred Aristide packet (Box 2)
    - Not in Their Best Interest: A Report on the U.S. Government's Forcible Repatriation of Guantanamo's Unaccompanied Haitian Children, 1995 May (Box 3)
    - Guantanamo packet, 1995 Feb., 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Guantanamo packet - update, 1995 Mar. 22 (Box 3)
    - P. Coven meeting 1996, Aug. 2 (Box 3)
    - Petitions/Letters of support (Box 3)
    - Post-Guantanamo (Box 3)
    - Press conferences, 1995 (Box 3)
      Guantanamo Children, Jan. 24, March 8, March 31, May 22, June 29, July 31.
    - Press: general file (Box 3)
    - Press Releases, 1994 Dec. 12 and 1996 April 1 (Box 3)
    - Guantanamo processing, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Resolutions (Box 3)
    - Special immigrant status for foster children (Box 3)
    - Supplemental information, 1994-1996, Guantanamo, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - UNHCR correspondence (Box 3)
    - Update reports (Box 3)
    - US Commission on Civil Rights testimony, 1994-1995 (Box 81)
  - Krome Subseries, 1982-2000
    Subseries contains materials related to Krome detention facility, including some material on children's asylum claims. The subseries includes affidavits, articles, correspondence, reports about facility conditions and policies, information on the hunger strike, and court cases files.
    - 79th St. Incident, 1990 July (Box 4)
    - Abuse/ILEMP/Krome, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Abuses, 1989, 1991, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Abuses at Krome, 1989, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Access to Krome, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Krome Affidavits, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Affidavits of Abuse, 1989-1991 (Box 4)
    - Affidavits and Articles, pp.1-220, 10 folders (Box 4)
    - Affidavit: Medcraft (Box 5)
    - Affidavits - no names, incl. rape (Box 5)
    - Transfer Affs and others, 1991 April 4 (Box 5)
    - Airport Ct. 1996-1997 (Box 5)
    - Akburak, Nazim (Box 5)
    - Amnesty International 1989-1993 (Box 5)
    - Articles and letters, 1986-1992 (Box 5)
    - Articles/reports/letters 1991-1994 (Box 5)
      Re: Haiti issues.
    - Article, Haiti: An Island Between Seasons, Shacocks, Bob. Harper's Bazaar, 1987 Feb. (Box 5)
    - Articles re: Krome, 1990-1996 (Box 5)
    - Article, Spirit-Murdering the Messenger, Williams, Patricia. (Box 5)
    - Articles on sexual abuse, 1990-2002 (Box 81)
    - Krome, Attorney Access, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Krome Background, 1996 (Box 5)
    - Chiles v. Moore, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Concerns at Krome, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, Krome, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, Krome, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 2002 (Box 6)
    - Deaths at Krome, 1999-2001 (Box 81)
    - Detainee handbook, 2000s (Box 81)
    - Detention Forum, 1996 Feb. 16 (Box 6)
    - Double standard, 1986-1990 (Box 6)
    - Tony Ebibillio Epken (Box 6)
    - Ebibillo Tony (Box 6)
    - Fat Pack II (Box 6)
    - FIAC booth or workspace, 2002-2003 (Box 81)
    - Removal of FIAC office, 2002-2003 (Box 81)
    - FOIA - investigation on Krome, 1998 (Box 6)
    - FTCA, 1991 (Box 6)
    - Graham v Smith, 1980-1981 (Box 82)
      Scope and Contents
      A lawsuit between plaintiffs Bob Graham, the Governor of FL, and others vs the Reagan administration represented by William French Smith, US attorney general. The suit is related to conditions at Krome.
    - Haitian Arrivals, 1998 May 16 (Box 6)
    - José Humberto Herrera. His personal experiences while being detained at Krome c. 1, 1989 (Box 97, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0008)
    - HRC v. Reno, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Hunger strike, 1991 (Box 7)
    - Hunger strike, 1992-1993 (Box 7)
    - Hunger strike, 2002 (Box 81)
    - Informational, inside Krome, policies and more, 1998 (Box 7)
    - INS detention standards (Box 7)
    - INS detention standards, 1998 (Box 7)
    - INS guidelines for children's asylum claims, 1998 (Box 7)
    - Kattola v. Reno, 3 of 6 folders (Box 7)
    - Kattola v. Reno, 3 of 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Kattola v Reno, 1992-1997 (Box 72)
      Documents regarding the case of Faiq Marrogi Kattola et al vs Janet Reno, the US Attorney General at the time. It contains primarily depositions for the case, lawsuit with multiple detention cases with migrants from various countries where the primary complaint is extended or indefinite detention, mostly at Krome but also other detention centers and county jails.
    - Kattola v Reno, 1996-1998 (Box 95)
      Documents regarding the case of Faiq Marrogi Kattola et al vs Janet Reno, the US Attorney General at the time. It contains primarily depositions for the case, lawsuit with multiple dentention cases with migrants from multiple countries where the primary complaint is extended or indefinite detention, mostly at Krome but also other detention centers and county jails.
    - Krome 1982 (Box 8)
    - Krome 1986 (Box 8)
    - Krome 1987 (Box 8)
    - Krome 1988 (Box 8)
    - Krome 1989, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Krome 1990 (Box 9)
    - Krome, 1990 April 12 (Box 9)
      Haitian complaints against Krome detention center.
    - Krome, 1990-1991 (Box 9)
    - Krome, 1992 (Box 9)
    - Krome, 1996 (Box 9)
      Includes Krome tour, 1996 April.
    - Krome, 1999, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Krome's Invisible Prisoners: Cycles of Abuse and Neglect, 1996 July (Box 9)
    - Krome reports (Box 9)
    - Krome Organization Intervention Report, 1997 (Box 9)
    - Krome Report, 1991, 1 of 5 (Box 9)
    - Krome Report, 1991, 2-5 of 5 (Box 10)
    - Krome Report, final originals, 1991 June (Box 10)
    - Krome update urgent action letters (Box 10)
    - Letters from HRC attorneys to INS officials and others, Krome (Box 10)
    - Letters from politicians, Krome (Box 10)
      Treatment of Haitian refugees.
    - Memos DDJ (Box 10)
    - Misc. Krome and TGK, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Model motion (Box 10)
    - Newspaper articles, Krome (Box 10)
    - Notes (Box 10)
    - Official Transcript Proceedings before The Supreme Court of the U.S., Gene McNary V HRC ct A1-89-1332, 1990, Oct. 10 (Box 10)
    - Overcrowding, 2006-2007 (Box 81)
    - Parole, 1991-1992 (Box 10)
    - Persecution of Haitian Returnees and Inadequacy of INS Pre-Screening Procedure, 1992 (Box 10)
    - Political Asylum Issues, 1989 (Box 10)
    - Rape case (Box 10)
    - Rape case, Marie Baptiste (Box 10)
    - Returnees/interviews, for copy, 1992 Feb.-March (Box 10)
    - Simao, Hermes Santos Jr. (Box 11)
    - Stepick - Haitians released from Krome, 1984 (Box 11)
    - Stowaways (Box 11)
    - Supplement, Krome, 1998, 6 folders (Box 11)
    - Supplemental articles and statements, Krome (Box 11)
    - Testimony of Cong. Carrie P. Meek, 1994 June 15 (Box 11)
    - Update, Krome, 1996-1997, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Update, Krome, 1999 (Box 11)
    - Wislaine Theresia's baby case (Box 11)
  - Turner Guilford Knight (TGK) Correctional Center Subseries, undated
    Subseries contains materials related to Turner Guilford Knight (TGK) Correctional Center.
    - Abraham - Prof. (Box 12)
    - Alternative setting for detainees (Box 12)
    - Annual review, 2004 (Box 79)
    - FIAC correspondence (Box 12)
    - General information (Box 12)
    - Inspection report, 2000-2004 (Box 79)
    - Memos/articles (Box 12)
    - TGK forms (Box 12)
    - TGK miscellaneous (Box 12)
    - Packet (Box 12)
    - Pro Bono (Box 12)
    - TGK report (Box 12)
    - Support groups/TGK (Box 12)
    - Urgent action/sign-on (Box 12)
  - County Jails Subseries, 1993-2000
    Subseries contains materials related to Florida county jails. The subseries mainly includes affidavits and reports on facility conditions.
    - Abandoned: The Betryal of America's Immigrants, 55 minute documentary on anti-immigrant sentiment, unfair treatment and policies for immigrants in detention and facing deportation. Produced by Crowing Rooster Arts, Inc. Filmed in Atlanta, GA; Miami, FL; York, PA; El Paso, TX; Washington DC and New York City. Contains FIAC's footage of county jails., 2000 (Box 97, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0001)
    - Complaint letter about the county jail to Representative Ros-Lehtinen (Box 13)
    - County jails visit, 1999 July (Box 13)
    - County jails affidavits, 1996-1997 (Box 13)
    - Affidavits, 1998 (Box 13)
    - Affidavits continued, 1998 (Box 13)
    - Affidavits, 2000 (Box 13)
    - Affidavits - Key West, 1998 (Box 13)
      Originals.
    - Baker county, 2012-2015 (Box 81)
    - Conditions, 2003 (Box 81)
    - County jail articles (Box 13)
    - County jail's conditions (Box 13)
      Citrus/Hornando/Manatee.
    - Conditions at Varick Street Immigration Detention Center, 1993 (Box 13)
    - County Jail - detainees' letters, affidavits, etc., 1998 (Box 13)
    - County jails, 1999 (Box 13)
    - County jails - Florida (Box 13)
      Pending.
    - Florida County Jails: INS's Secret Detention World, 1997 Nov. (Box 13)
    - Glades county, 2003-2009 (Box 81)
    - Jackson County Jail (Box 14)
    - Jackson County Jail affidavits (Box 14)
    - Jackson county jails inspection reports, FOIA reports, etc., 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Jackson County Jail notes: detainees (Box 14)
    - Manatee County Jail (Box 14)
    - Oakdale (Box 14)
    - Pike County Jail (Box 14)
    - Private prisons/Kendall (Box 14)
    - Report on county jails, drafts (Box 14)
    - County jail supplement, 1998, 1 of 3 (Box 14)
    - County jail supplement, 1999 (Box 14)
  - General Subseries, 1987-2009
    Subseries contains materials related to general detention issues of interest to the FIAC. The subseries mainly includes documents regarding detention procedures and abuses and cases of indefinite detention.
    - Affidavit and client information, expedited removal, 1992-1997 (Box 15)
    - Berks contract, 2002 (Box 79)
    - Detention, 1990-1991 (Box 15)
    - Detention abuses, 1987-1991, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Detention meetings and concerns, 2007-2008 (Box 79)
    - Dying For Decent Care: Bad Medicine in Immigration Custody, 2009 Feb. (Box 15)
    - Indefinite detention, 1997-1999, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - INS detainees in Florida, 2001 (Box 15)
    - INS detainees in Florida, supplement, 2002 (Box 15)
    - INS detention, 1989-1990 (Box 16)
    - INS detention, 1996-1997, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - INS procedures, 1993-1995 (Box 16)
    - Post-custody review, undated (Box 16)
- Immigrants and Refugees Series, 1980-2004
  Series contains documents related to immigrant and refugee populations of interest to FIAC, particularly Haitian populations. Files primarily deal with issues of deportation and asylum, as well as issues relating to US detention. Files include legal documents such as affidavits and court records and other materials such as newspaper articles, correspondence, government reports, and PR materials. Sensitive and confidential material has been moved to the Restricted Files series. Files are arranged in rough alphabetical order.
  - Cubans Subseries, 1994-2009
    Subseries includes files related to AIJ's work on behalf of Cuban immigrants, most notably Elián González and the case of Campos vs INS which dealt with the naturalization process and mental and physical disabilities.
    - CABA v Christopher, 1994 (Box 79)
      CABA vs Christopher is a major lawsuit that the set precedent for Guantanamo policy and was filed on behalf of over 30,000 Cuban refugees, aka balseros, interdicted at sea and detained at Guantanamo Naval Base. The Cuban American Bar Association filed the lawsuit against the Clinton administration represented by Warren Christopher, Secretary of State. The suit cites the refugees' rights under the Cuban Adjustment Act of 1966 and the "unsanitary, deplorable and medically inadequate detention camps" at the base.
    - Elián González case, 2000-2001 (Box 87)
      Legal documents, news articles, and press releases related to the highly publicized case of Elián González, a Cuban child rescued at sea after losing his mother and step father in their attempt to reach Miami. His case drew wide spread public attention and debate, sparking a contensious custody battle between his father in Cuba and relatives in Miami.
    - South Florida Humanitarian Network for Cuba, early 2000s (Box 87)
    - Cuban detainees holding hostages in a Louisana jail, 1999 (Box 87)
    - Cuban detainee statements, 1998-2006 (Box 87)
    - Miscellaneous articles and legal documents related to Cuban migration, 2003-2009 (Box 87)
    - Dry foot wet foot policy, 1999-2009 (Box 87)
    - Trujillo v Reno, 1998-1999 (Box 90)
      Legal documents related to the class action lawsuit brought forward by Edilma Trujillo et al against US Attorney General Janet Reno and other Clinton administration and federal officials. The lawsuit covers mostly Cuban elderly and disabled naturalization applicants caught in "naturalization limbo" because their naturalization process had been uncessarily delayed without proper notification or reasoning.
    - Campos v INS, 1996-2000 (Box 91)
      A class action lawsuit brought forward by primarily Cuban elderly, disabled, and ill immigrants denied medical exemption and fee waiver for the English requirement of their naturalization test and some were also then denied citizenship.
    - Campos v INS, 1994-2000 (Box 92)
      A class action lawsuit brought forward by primarily Cuban elderly, disabled, and ill immigrants denied medical exemption and fee waivers for the English requirement of their naturalization test and some were also then denied citizenship.
    - Campos v INS, 1998-1999 (Box 67)
  - Haitians Subseries, 1981-2011